Fabio Miranda

ASSISTANT PROFESSOR, DEPARTMENT OF COMPUTER SCIENCE, COLLEGE OF ENGINEERING

University of Illinois at Chicago

851 S. Morgan St, MC 152, Chicago, IL, 60607

□ (+1) 347-545-6405 | **S** fabiom@uic.edu | **A** fmiranda.me

Research Interests

I am interested in developing techniques that allow for the interactive visual analysis of large-scale data, combining methods from visualization, data management, machine learning and computer graphics. I have worked closely with domain experts from different fields and the outcome of these collaborations included not only research published in leading venues, but also systems that were made available to experts in academia, industry and government agencies. My work has also received extensive coverage from different media outlets, including The New York Times, The Economist, Architectural Digest, Curbed, among others.

Education

2012 - 2018 Ph.D. in Computer Science

New York, NY, USA

New York University (NYU) Advised by Cláudio T. Silva.

Dissertation: "Data structures for the interactive visual analysis of urban data".

2009 - 2011 M.S. in Computer Science

Rio de Janeiro, RJ, Brazil

Pontifical Catholic University of Rio de Janeiro (PUC-Rio)

Advised by Waldemar Celes.

Thesis: "Volume rendering of unstructured hexahedral meshes".

2005 - 2009 B.S. in Computer Science

Belo Horizonte, MG, Brazil

Federal University of Minas Gerais (UFMG)

Advised by Luiz Chaimowicz.

Professional Experience

Fall 2020 - present University of Illinois at Chicago

Chicago, IL, USA

Assistant Professor, Department of Computer Science, College of Engineering

Fall 2018 - Fall 2020 New York University

New York, NY, USA

Postdoctoral researcher

Development of new techniques for the interactive visualization of different types of large-scale data, such as streaming timeseries data and image data. Also responsible for mentoring PhD students.

Summer 2016 Argonne National Laboratory

Lemont, IL, USA

Research intern

Mentor: Venkatram Vishwanath

Developed a visualization tool to explore high-resolution volumetric weather simulations, focused in the Chicago metropolitan area, in order to understand the impact of built environment on the city climate.

Summer 2015 IBM T.J. Watson Research Center

Yorktown Heights, NY, USA

Research intern

Mentor: Bruce D'Amora

Developed a web-based graph visualization tool for the exploratory visualization of bitcoin transactions.

Summer 2014 AT&T Research

Middletown, NJ, USA

Research intern

Mentors: Lauro Lins and James Klosowski

Developed a distributed version of *Nanocubes*, a datacube-based approach for the visualization of massive spatiotemporal datasets.

FABIO MIRANDA · CURRICULUM VITAE

1

Summer 2013 Sandia National Laboratories Albuquerque, NM, USA

Research intern

Mentor: Patricia Crossno

Developed an adaptive kernel density estimation approach for scatterplots using GPUs.

2009 - 2012 **TecGraf / PUC-Rio**

Rio de Janeiro, Brazil

Research assistant Mentor: Waldemar Celes

Developed an unstructured hexahedral volume renderer for a data visualization and analysis software

used in most of Brazil's oil fields.

Awards

2018 SIGMOD Best Demonstration Award

For "Interactive Visual Exploration of Spatio-Temporal Urban Data Sets Using Urbane".

2018 Pearl Brownstein Doctoral Research Award

For doctoral research that shows the greatest promise, awarded by NYU.

2010-2012 CAPES and Petrobras Fellowships

Awarded during M.S. studies.

2006-2009 FINEP and CNPq Fellowships

Awarded during B.S. studies.

Selected Media Coverage

September 2017 Urban Pulse Uses Social Media Data to Show Cities in a New Light

Architectural Digest 🗗

September 2017 New program wants to improve cities with the power of tweets and Flickr uploads

Curbed 2

December 2016 Mapping the Shadows of New York City: Every Building, Every Block

The New York Times 🗷

October 2016 Listen to the music of the traffic in the city

The Economist 🗷

Publications

2021 UrbanRama: Navigating Cities in Virtual Reality

S. Chen, **F. Miranda**, N. Ferreira, M. Lage, H. Doraiswamy, C. Brenner, C. Defanti, M. Koutsoubis, L. Wilson, K. Perlin, C. Silva

IEEE Transactions on Visualization and Computer Graphics (accepted, to appear)

2020 Urban Mosaic: Visual Exploration of Streetscapes Using Large-scale Image Data

F. Miranda, M. Lage, H. Doraiswamy, M. Hosseini, G. Dove, C. T. Silva

2020 CHI Conference on Human Factors in Computing Systems.

Learning Geo-Contextual Embeddings for Commuting Flow Prediction

Z. Liu, F. Miranda, W. Xiong, J. Yang, Q. Wang, C. T. Silva

Thirty-Fourth AAAI Conference on Artificial Intelligence.

2019 Shadow Accrual Maps: Efficient Accumulation of City-Scale Shadows over Time

F. Miranda, H. Doraiswamy, M. Lage, L. Wilson, M. Hsieh, C. T. Silva

IEEE Transactions on Visualization and Computer Graphics, vol. 25, no. 3, pp. 1559-1574, Mar 2019.

Featured on The New York Times

2018 Time Lattice: A Data Structure for the Interactive Visual Analysis of Large Time Series

F. Miranda, M. Lage, H. Doraiswamy, C. Mydlarz, J. Salamon, Y. Lockerman, J. Freire, C. T. Silva *Computer Graphics Forum, vol. 37, no. 3, pp. 23-35, Jun 2018.*

Interactive Visual Exploration of Spatio-Temporal Urban Data Sets using Urbane

H. Doraiswamy, E. Tzirita Zacharatou, **F. Miranda**, M. Lage, A. Ailamaki, C. T. Silva, J. Freire *2018 ACM SIGMOD Intl. Conf. on Management of Data - Demo.*

Best Demonstration Award

Spatio-Temporal Urban Data Analysis: A Visual Analytics Perspective

H. Doraiswamy, J. Freire, M. Lage, **F. Miranda**, C. T. Silva

IEEE Computer Graphics and Application, vol. 38, no. 5, pp. 26-35, Sept/Oct 2018.

TopKube: A Rank-Aware Data Cube for Real-Time Exploration of Spatiotemporal Datasets

F. Miranda, L. Lins, J. Klosowski, C. T. Silva

IEEE Transactions on Visualization and Computer Graphics, vol. 24, no. 3, pp. 1394-1407, Mar 2018.

2017 Urban Pulse: Capturing the Rhythm of Cities

F. Miranda, H. Doraiswamy, M. Lage, K. Zao, B. Goncalves, L. Wilson, M. Hsieh, C. T. Silva *IEEE Transactions on Visualization and Computer Graphics, vol. 23, no. 1, pp. 791-800, Jan 2017.*

Featured on The Economist, invited to SIGGRAPH 2017 TVCG special session

Data Visualization Tool for Monitoring Transit Operation and Performance

A. Kurkcu, F. Miranda, K. Ozbay, C. T. Silva

5th IEEE Intl. Conf. on Models and Technologies for Intelligent Transportation Systems (2017).

TopKube: A Rank-Aware Data Cube for Real-Time Exploration of Spatiotemporal Datasets

F. Miranda, L. Lins, J. Klosowski, C. T. Silva

Data Systems for Interactive Analysis (DSIA) 2016.

Volume Rendering of Unstructured Hexahedral Meshes

F. Miranda, and W. Celes

The Visual Computer Journal, vol. 28, no. 10, pp. 1005-1014, Oct 2012.

2011 Accurate Volume Rendering of Unstructured Hexahedral Meshes

F. Miranda, and W. Celes

24th Sibgrapi Conference on Graphics, Patterns and Images (2011).

Illustrative Volume Visualization for Unstructured Meshes Based on Photic Extremum Lines

A. Rocha, F. Miranda, and W. Celes

24th Sibgrapi Conference on Graphics, Patterns and Images (2011).

Teaching Experience

Spring 2021 CS425: Computer Graphics I

University of Illinois at Chicago

Undergraduate course.

Fall 2019 CS GY 6533: Interactive Computer Graphics

New York University

Graduate course. Prepared and presented 2.5 hour lecture on shadows.

Fall 2014 CS UY 1133: Data Structures and Algorithms

New York University

Undergraduate course. Prepared and presented 2.5 hour lecture on C and C++ programming.

Fall 2014 CUSP GX 5003: Principles of Urban Informatics

New York University

Teaching assistant for Cláudio T. Silva, 50 students

Graduate course. Prepared and presented lectures on visualization, python, pandas and MySQL. Created and graded assignments, and held office hours.

Fall 2013 CUSP GX 5003: Principles of Urban Informatics

New York University

Teaching assistant for Cláudio T. Silva, 50 students

Graduate course. Developed and presented lectures on visualization, python, javascript, D3 and MySQL. Prepared and graded assignments, and held office hours.

Mentoring Experience

2018 - Mentor Ph.D. Students

New York University

Mentor students to work with the Urbane framework, as well as on research projects.

Students: Zhicheng Liu (CS PhD student at Southeast University, China), Maryam Hosseini (Urban Systems PhD student at Rutgers), Shaoyu Chen (CS PhD student at NYU), João Rulff (CS PhD student at NYU).

Invited Talks and Presentations

Interactive Visual Analysis of Urban Data: Beyond Flatland April 2021 Online Department of Energy Computer Graphics Forum 2021 Department of Energy **Interactive Visual Analysis of Urban Data: A Computational** April 2021 Porto Alegre, RS, Brazil **Perspective on Cities** Federal University of Rio Grande do Sul **Interactive Visual Analysis of Urban Data: A Computational** March 2021 Niteroi, RJ, Brazil **Perspective on Cities** Fluminense Federal University Interactive Visual Analysis at Scale: From Data to Actionable February 2020 Chicago, CA, USA University of Illinois at Chicago Interactive Visual Analysis at Scale: From Data to Actionable February 2020 Chicago, IL, USA **Insights** Illinois Institute of Technology Interactive Visual Analysis at Scale: From Data to Actionable February 2020 San Diego, CA, USA **Insights** San Diego State University Interactive Visual Analysis at Scale: From Data to Actionable February 2020 New Orleans, LA, USA **Insights Tulane University** Interactive Visual Analysis at Scale: From Data to Actionable February 2020 New Orleans, LA, USA **Insights** The University of New Orleans Interactive Visual Analysis at Scale: From Data to Actionable January 2020 Portland, OR, USA **Insights**

University of Massachusetts - Dartmouth

Virginia Commonwealth University

Portland State University

Insights

Insights

January 2020

January 2020

Interactive Visual Analysis at Scale: From Data to Actionable

Interactive Visual Analysis at Scale: From Data to Actionable

Richmond, VA, USA

Dartmouth, MA, USA

Exploration of Street-Level Images at Scale December 2018 New York City, NY, USA Pedestrian Movement Technology Showcase at Metro North **Shadow Accrual Maps: Efficient Accumulation of City-Scale** November 2018 Berlin, Germany **Shadows over Time** IEEE Visualization Conference (VIS) Time Lattice: A Data Structure for the Interactive Visual June 2018 Brno, Czech Republic **Analysis of Large Time Series** EG/VGTC Conference on Visualization (EuroVis) TopKube: A Rank-Aware Data Cube for Real-Time Exploration of October 2017 Phoenix, AZ, USA **Spatiotemporal Datasets** IEEE Visualization Conference (VIS) September 2016 **Visualizing and Exploring Urban Data** Boston, MA, USA **Data Visualization Summit** TopKube: A Rank-Aware Data Cube for Real-Time Exploration of October 2016 Chicago, IL, USA **Spatiotemporal Datasets** Data Systems for Interactive Analysis Workshop (DSIA) **Accurate Volume Rendering of Unstructured Hexahedral** October 2011 Maceió, Brazil **Meshes** Sibgrapi Conference on Graphics, Patterns and Images

Selected Open-Source Projects

2019 New York City Shadow Data

Shadow data for New York City, also used by The New York Times. 🗹

2018 Urban Pulse

Open-source version of Urban Pulse paper.

2017 Bus Explorer

Open-source tool for the exploration of a large data set with bus tracking pings. Developed in close collaboration with the New York City Department of Transportation.

Professional Service

Program Committees: Sibgrapi (2019, 2020, 2021), IEEE VIS Short papers (2019, 2020, 2021). Reviewer: VLDB, IEEE Transactions on Visualization and Computer Graphics, IEEE Transactions on Big Data, IEEE InfoVis, IEEE SciVis, IEEE VAST, Sibgrapi, WWW, The Visual Computer Journal, Transportation Research Record Journal, International Journal of Geo-Information, International Conference on Pattern Recognition.

University Service

Discovery Partners Institute grant reviewer (2021).

Written Critique and Presentation committees: Carla Floricel (2021), Md Nafiul Alam Nipu (2021), Andrew Wentzel (2021), Muhammad Abdul Wahhab (2021)

Master's Project committees: Parikshit Solunke (2021), Pavana Doddi (2021)

Graduate Admission Committee (2020, 2021).

Provost's Graduate Research Award reviewer (2020).

Outreach Activities

Chicago Area Undergraduate Research Symposium judge (2021).

Professional Memberships

Association for Computing Machinery (ACM). Brazilian Computer Society (Sociedade Brasileira de Computação, SBC).